Guide to the Karl Menger Papers, 1872-2000 RL.00888
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Correspondence Series, 1918-1984; 1
  - General correspondence, "H", 1920-1983 and undated (Box 2)
    Including: Wilhelm (?) Hummel (dimension theory, set theory); Edmund Husserl (postcard, routine exchanges); Arend Heyting (thanks for reprints, Brouwer); Felix Hausdorff (thanks for reprints, Brouwer-Menger controversy); Lothar Heffter (illegible); T. Hirano (foundations of mathematics, Herman Weyl, Gödel); T.H. Hildebradt (thanks for warm treatment at Notre Dame conference, Green's theorem); Victor F. Hess (routine exchanges, Gert Müller); Lilly Hahn (Hans Hahn, routine exchanges); M. Herfeld (Emil Kauder, Carl Menger, Crown Prince Rudolph, Menger's paper about Carl and Rudolph); Car; G. Hempel (regarding whether Princeton's math department ever used one of Menger's texts, thanks for reprints, mathematical eduction / pedagogy); Edward F. Haskell (sent reprints, Marston Morse, geometry); George B. Headley (mathematics education / pedagogy); M.E. Hartzler (thanks for reprints, comments, applied statistics, routine exchanges); Martial (?) Honnell (mathematics education / pedagogy, electrical engineering, Laplace transformations); Father Henry (?) (1960 summer institute on mathematics education (?), theory of planar order); Albert Hardwick (Associate Editor Charles E. Merrill Books, routine exchanges); Nikolaus Hofreiter (routine exchanges, approval of University of Vienna Fulbright proposal); Dietmar Hübler (projective geometry); Maurice Heiss (?) (Riemannian geometry); J.B. Harkin (routine exchanges, printing of book, Marquette project update); Adolf Hübner (routine exchanges); Rudolf Haller (routine exchanges, Holder-Pichler-Tempsky); F. Henmuller (?) (planar geometry ?)
  - Isaacs, Rufus, 1947-1952 and undated (Box 2)
    American game theorist.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; request for advice; comments on paper; differential games
  - Johnson, Dale M., 1972-1981 and undated (Box 2)
    American mathematician; author of book on history of dimension theory. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Topic(s): Johnson's book on history of dimension theory; Brouwer-Menger-Urysohn priority controversy
  - Journal of Graph Theory, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    Topic(s): Thank you to Menger for willingness to contribute to special issue dedicated to his work, correspondence regarding same
  - General correspondence, "J", 1929-1975 (Box 2)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with J.
    Including: Vojtěch Jarník (comments on Menger's "Dimensionstheorie"); Easley S. Jones (request for reading suggestions regarding theory of abstract groups; John C. Jordan (mathematical / statistical meteorology); Ralph Duncan James (revisions to Menger's paper "Gulliver's Return to the Land Without One, Two, Three"); Frederick H. Jackson (rejection of appeal for Carnegie funding); Bjarni Jonsson (lattice theory); Larry Johnson (Everiste Galois, nutrition, routine exchanges)
  - Kaufmann, Felix, 1927-1934 and undated (Box 2)
    Austrian-American philosopher; member of the Vienna Circle.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; Brouwer, Vienna Circle; social science methodology; thanks for copy of book (probably "Moral, Wille Und Weltgestaltung")
  - Knaster, Bronislaw, 1925-1936 (Box 2)
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; curve theory, set theory, dimension theory; Hurwicz, Urysohn, Brouwer, Alexandroff, Nöbeling, Ayres, R.L. Moore, Kuratowski, Borsuk, Aronzsajn, Hahn, Schreier; comments on papers
  - Kuratowski, Kazimierz, 1921-1960 (Box 2)
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; curve theory, set theory, dimension theory, topology; Urysohn, Brouwer, Alexandroff, Knaster, Wilder, Hahn, Sierpinski, Nöbeling, Gödel; 1960 invitation for Menger to visit Poland
  - General correspondence, "K", 1924-1982 and undated (Box 2)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with K.
    Including: M. Kiseljak (routine exchanges); A. Koselt (routine exchanges, handwriting illegibile); J.R. Kline (routine exchanges, request for reprints); H. Kinneth (curve theory; Dénes Kőnig (graph theory, curve theory); W.D. Kupradze (exchange of reprints); Julius Kraft ("Moral, Wille und Weltgestaltung"); Dick Kayser (routine exchanges); Howard K. (?) (routine exchanges); Ann Kontny (routine exchanges); Morton R. Kenner (1960 Sumer Institute for Teachers of Mathematics); Paul Kelly (thanks for reprints, job offer to UCSB); Richard Kessler (routine eschanges, compliments for course taught by Menger, "Kessler's equation"); Virginia Kafka (proofs, theorems); Erwin Kreyszig (routine exchanges); Hans (?) Kopfermann (regarding Menger's manuscript "Weierstrass Analytic Functions and Riemann Surfaces"); R.G. Keats (routine exchanges); Hedi Kuranda (from Menger, routine exchanges); Robert Kowalski (routine exchanges); Burt Kaufman (Comprehensive School Mathematics Program); Eckehart Kohler (routine exchanges, Gödel, Schimanovich, Carnap, Dingler, Wittgenstein, methodological tolerance); Rudolf Kirchschlaeger (80th birthday wishes); postcard from (? handwriting illegible) (routine exchanges); K. Kunngui (partial letter); Marianne Kuranda (routine exchanges); C.J.K. (?) (Notre Dame engineering qualifying exams)
  - Lefschetz, Solomon, 1930-1944 (Box 2)
    Topic(s): Invitation to lecture; routine exchanges; Nöbeling's result concerning deformation of homeopathic n-dimensional sets in 2n+2 dimensional space; rejection letter from Annals of Mathematics
  - Littauer, Sebastian, 1931-1937 and undated (Box 2)
    American engineer.
    Topic(s): Request for letter of recommendation; routine exchanges; request for reprints
  - General correspondence, "L", 1927-1982 and undated (Box 2)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with L.
    Including: R.G. Lubben (routine exchanges); Edgar Ovell Lovett (visitng appointment to Rice Institute); Adölf Lindenbaum (offprints sent); letter from (? handwriting illegible) (offprints received / sent); P. Lévy (routine exchanges); Adrienne Lipson (discussion of results, computer program for 3 functor results); John B. Lennes (invitation to lecture); Werner Leinfellner (symposiums on Wittgenstein and Vienna Circle); Eric F. Lype (routine exchanges, 80th birthday wishes); J. Marianne Littau (communication of recent mathematical results); May Ling (photographs)
  - Mandelbroit, Benoit B., 1978 and undated (Box 3)
    Polish-American mathematician. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Topic(s): From Menger: complaint for not receiving credit for discovering, defining, and proving universlaity of Menger sponge in Mandelbroit's book "Fractals." From Mandelbroit: apologies and correction.
  - Mayer, Anton E., 1935-1936 and undated (Box 3)
    Austrian mathematician
    Topic(s): Projective geometry; handwritten copy of Mayer's "Der grosse durchmesser koveklaieller (?) Polygone"
  - Mazurkiewicz, Stefan, 1929-1934 (Box 3)
    Topic(s): Dimension theory; invitation to lecture; routine exchanges
  - McGuinness, Brian, 1974-1980 (Box 3)
    British philosopher; editor of Vienna Circle Collection.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; correspondence regarding Vienna Circle Collection; Boltzmann, Wittgenstein, Hahn
  - Menger's outgoing correspondence to unknown recipients, 1922-1975 and undated (Box 3)
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; dimension theory, set theory; Hurwicz, Blumenthal, Wald, Gödel; Brouwer-Menger-Urysohn controversy; possible book on philosophy of mathematics; Menger's philosophical library; comments on unidentified papers
  - Moore, Robert Lee, 1926-1930 (Box 3)
    Topic(s): Thanks for reprints, reprints sent to Menger; curve theory; routine exchanges; invitation to lecture at U. of Texas during Menger's visit to Rice Institute
  - Morgenstern, Oskar, 1952-1977 (Box 3)
    Austrian economist; founder (with John von Neumann) of game theory; member of Menger's Mathematical Colloquium. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; thanks for reprints; potential resarch contract for Menger; Emil Kauder; Morgenstern encourages Menger to re-commence work on his mathematical ethics à la "Moral, Wille und Weltgestaltung" and to get Menger's Petersburg Paradox paper translated into English; Menger's research project on social groups and relations
  - Morris, Charles W., 1934-1975 (Box 3)
    American philosopher.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; request to meet while Morris visits Vienna; invitation to Menger to attend Chicago Logic of Science Disucssion Group
  - Morse, Marston, 1934-1957 and undated (Box 3)
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; thanks for reprints; Blumenthal, Veblen, Gödel; metric geometry,calculus of variations; acceptance of invitation to lecture at Notre Dame; copy of correspondence from Morse to Gordon Bowles, Executive Secretary, Conference Board of Associated Research Coucils, regarding Menger; submission of manuscript to Proceedings of the American Mathematical Society; thanks for copy of "Calculus"; correspondence with Edward Haskell regarding Menger
  - Mulder, Henk, 1972-1978 (Box 3)
    Dutch philosopher.
    Topic(s): Neurath, Carnap; Vienna Circle Collection, correspondence regarding Menger's contribution to VCC and partcipation as Advisory Board member; routine exchanges
  - General correspondence, "M", 1933-1980 and undated (Box 3)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with M.
    Including: H.M. Miller (Rockefeller Foundation administrator regarding fellowship for Nöbeling); Yukio Mimura (routine exchanges); H. Marsh (?) (routine exchanges); Paul Montes (routine exchanges); Richard von Mises (Wald, foundations of probability theory); H. Mark (Philipp Gross); Kazuo K. Midutani (mathematical economics); G.H. (?) MIller (response to invitation to visit Notre Dame); Andrzej Mostowski (routine exchanges, Tarski, Polish exposition of Gödel's incompleteness theorems); Ho Kee Minn (routine exchanges); Edward F. Moody, Jr. (rejection from Wiley & Sons of "Calculus: A Modern Approach"); Warren Sturgis McCulloch (thanks for reprints, neurophysiology); Heinrich Meyer (partial letter, set theory, differential calculus, group theory, function theory, Bridgman); Russell Meyers, M.D. (comments on Menger's "Why Johnny Hates Math" and "New Approach to Teaching Intermediate Mathematics"); Fritz Machlup (routine exchanges, possible gift of Menger's collection of photographs [of economists?] to Johns Hopkins); Daniel M. McMaster (correspondence from Lawrence J. Green, S.J. regarding geometry exhibition at Chicago Museum of Science and Industry); W.H. Meyer (regarding mathematics currciulum of California public high schools); Edwin Marcuski (?) (response to invitation to conference); Maximilian Mintz (thanks for reprints, routine exchanges); Kenneth O. May (thanks for Menger's offer to write something on theory of curves; routine exchanges); M.A. McKiernan (calculus of variations, mauscript of McKiernan's "Sufficiency of Parameter Invariance Conditions in Areal and Higher Order Kawaguchi Spaces); William M. Myers (request for suggestion of candidates for position at University of Montana); Saunders Mac Lane (routine exchanges); Marvin G. Mundt (routine exchanges); Klaus Mudersbach (routine exchanges, thanks for reprints, definition); Phil Marcus (reprints sent); Eva Menger (daughter) (routine exchanges); Kirsten Menger (-Anderson, granddaughter) (routine exchanges); Dr. Mahavier (?) (from Menger, routine exchanges, discussion of formula); Karl S. Menger, Jr. (son) (routine exchanges)
  - Neumann, John von, 1930-1953 and undated (Box 3)
    Hungarian mathematician, physicist, and economist; founder (with Oskar Morgenstern) of game theory.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; reprints sent, thanks for reprints
  - Newman, James R., 1956-1959 (Box 3)
    Topic(s): Correspondence regarding Menger's proposed article for Scientific American; comments on Menger's "mathematics primer" ("Why Johnny Hates Math"?)
  - Nöbeling, Georg, 1929-1934 and undated (Box 3)
    German mathematician; member of Menger's Mathematical Colloquium.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; mathematical colloquium; geometry, topology, analysis, curve theory, dimension theory, set theory, differential calculus; letter of recommendation written by Menger on Nöbeling's behalf; Wald, Urysohn, Reichenbach, Grell, Hahn, Alt, Hurwicz, Bieberbach, Flores, Veblen, A.N. Whitehead, F.K. Schmidt, Kurt Reidemeister, Čech
  - General correspondence, "N", 1926-1975 and undated (Box 3)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with N. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Including: Ernst Nagel, Otton Nikodym (routine exchanges, reprints); Otto Neurath (Encyclopedia of Unified Science); F.S. Norlan (?) (home rental); Ernest Nagel (comments on partial manuscript of Menger's "Mathematics and Common Sense"); Eric T. Nettel (routine exchanges); M.H.A. "Max" Newman (thanks for offprints, Bertrand Russell)
  - Office of Naval Research, 1963 (Box 3)
    Topic(s): Proposal on algebra of functions
  - Oldenbourg Verlag, R., 1964-1981 (Box 3)
    German publisher.
    Topic(s): Comments on Menger's "Calculus", "Selected Papers"; routine exchanges
  - Organizations (Miscellaneous), 1924-1978 and undated (Box 3)
    Topic(s): (Viennese ? Austrian ?) Akademie der Wissenschaften (Menger's deposit of "Point Set Theory III"); R. Gaston Dreyfus & Cie (account statement); Society for the Protection of Science and Learning (reference for Friedrich Waismann); Association for Symbolic Logic (invitation to join); Committee in Preparation for the 2nd International Topology Conference (committee business); Minerva Wissenschaftliche Buchhandlung (receipt); British Society for the History of Science, Philosophy of Science Group (correspondence regarding accepted paper); Chicago Museum of Science and Industry (mathematics exhibit); The Saturday Review (science / mathematics education); Canadian Journal of Mathematics (rejection letter); British Society for Philosophy of Science, et al. (correspondence [stapled together] apparently concerning Menger's trip ca. 1960/61 to Britain, includes letters from Mary Hesse, Martin Fieldhouse, Gerd Buchdahl, G.N. Copley, P.H. Frost, M.H.A. "Max" Newman); Archiv der Mathematik (corrections to manuscript ?); The International Year Book and Statesmen's Who's Who (Menger's biographical entry in the 1963 Year Book); Institute for Advanced Studies - Vienna (list of guest professors); Association for the Advancement of Science, 133rd Meeting (abstract for Menger's talk on Mach); Illinois Institute of Technology, Public Relations Department (list of upcoming events); Ex Libris Buchhandlungsgesellschaft (order of Menger's "Basic Concepts of Mathematics"); Harper and Brother (from Menger, regarding "Calculus. The Elements"); Kürschners Deutscher Gelehrten-Kalender (form / request for information); Theory and Decision (rotuine exchanges); Duncker and Humboldt (publication rights to works of Carl Menger); University of Vienna (program from symposium on 100 years of Carl Menger's "Grundsätze"); Battelle, Seattle Resarch Center ("An Open Letter from a Group of Mathematicians to Mr. Emerson Elliott, the Acting Director of the National Institute of Education"); Oxford University Press (order / billing of Hicks-Weber's book "Carl Menger"); CBS International Publishing (request to quote from textbook); Synthese (style sheet); B.G. Teubner Verlag (publishing contract); American Catholic's Who's Who (Menger's entry); Johann Rotter Cemetary (grave sales / advertising ?); Ford Institute in Vienna (structure and scope of Institute); Whos' Who in America (Menger's entry in the 43rd edition); American Men of Science (Menger's entry in the 1970 edition); Little City (seasons greetings card)
  - Ostrowski, Alexander, 1951-1955 (Box 3)
    Russian-Swiss mathematician.
    Topic(s): Menger's "Geometrie und Wahrscheinlichkeit"; comments on paper
  - General correspondence, "O", 1936-1954 and undated (Box 3)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with O.
    Including: Signature illegible (Lillruy Ogulral ?) (routine exchanges ?); Rufus Oldenburger (notes of Menger's seminar lecture, 1953 Sigma XI program); Benton Brooks Owen (request for reprint); Thomas H. Osgood (rejection letter from American Journal of Physics); Oystein Ore (rotuine exchanges); Bob Owendoff (vector analysis)
  - Pauc, Christian Yvon, 1933-1961 and undated (Box 3)
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; calculus of variations, topology, curve theory, dimension theory; Frechet, Brouwer, Wald, Bouligand
  - Philosophia Verlag, 1978-1984 and undated (Box 3)
    Albert H. Zlabinger; Carl Menger Library.
    Topic(s): Correspondence regarding Carl Menger Library; routine exchanges; Hayek, Ludwig von Mises, Ludwig Lachmann
  - Popoff, Kiril, 1930-1932 (Box 3)
    Bulgarian mathematician and physicist.
  - Popper, Karl R., 1968-1971 (Box 3)
    Austro-British philosopher.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; lattice theory; logical tolerance
  - General correspondence, "P", 1927-1982 (Box 3)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with P. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Including: M. Parch (Brouwer, handwriting illegible); Emil L. Post (reprint sent, routine exchanges); Josef Priebuh (dimension theory); James Pierpont (routine exchanges, thanks for reprints); William T. Perry (routine exchanges, Gödel); Rozsa Peter (thanks for reprints); G. Baley Price (routine exchanges, Green's Theorem); Dan Pyke (complaint regarding Menger's classification as a citizen of German, rather than Austrian, extraction); Gerald B. Phelan (routine exchanges, Menger's "The New Logic"); Sister Mary Peleu (?) (routine exchanges); Chaim Perelman (routine exchanges); George Kimball Plochmann (routine exchages; invitation for Menger to speak at 1964 Western Division meeting of American Philosophical Association); James Pettigrew (routine exchanges, time worked on Menger's research project); William A. Pierce (Moulton Plane); Tony Patricelli (correspondence stapled together, includes letters from Menger, Joe Harkin, and an unnamed ("Ed") correspondent, mathematics teaching, Menger's pre-limit calculus text); Robert Park (Menger [and Blumenthal's] "Studies in Geometry"); Jonas Partridge (treatment of American Indians); Solomon Passy (Bulgarian translation of Menger's "Wittgenstein on Formulae and Variables"); Pryozelaki (? signature illegible) (thanks for reprints)
  - Quine, Willard Van Orman, 1952 (Box 3)
    American philosopher and logician.
    Topic(s): Routine exchanges; praise for and comments upon Menger's attempt to reform calculus, and calculus textbook
  - D. Reidel Publishing Company, 1972-1980 and undated (Box 3)
    Publisher of Vienna Circle Collection.
    Topic(s): Regarding publication Vienna Circle Collection, Menger's contributions and others
  - Reilly, Robert C., 1963 (Box 3)
    Topic(s): Work on Menger's research project
  - General correspondence, "R", 1926-1977 and undated (Box 3)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with R. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Including: Bertrand Russell (routine exchanges, thanks for reprints, topology); Selby Robinson (request to work with Menger at University of Vienna, 1933-34, as a research assistant); Robert Reininger (routine exchanges); Tonio Rella (routine exchanges, Hahn); Alfred Rosenblatt (topology, mathematical astronomy, Godofredo Garcia, routine exchanges); R.G.D. Richardson (Menger's visit to New York); Hans Reichenbach (Carnap, possibility of a position for Menger in UCLA's math daepartment, thanks for reprints); A. Revuz (routine exchanges, Frechet); J.T. Rettaliata (routine exchanges, Howard Horvath); A. Rapoportz (?) (Menger's Calculus textbook, probabilistic geometry); Tibor Rado (routine exchanges, manuscript); Francois Rostand (routine exchanges, apologies for inability to respond positively to invitation); Gilbert Ryle (rejection letter); Professor Ryser (?) (from Menger, regarding commutative hypergroups); Nicolas Rashevsky (Robert Rosen's PhD defense); Frigyes Riesz (from Menger, regarding multivalued analytic functions); Robert Reichardt (Viennese Ford Institute lecture regarding street geometry (i.e., "taxicab geometry" ?); Gerald R. Rising (mathematics education); Stephen Regoczei (Waismann's "Introduction to Mathematical Thinking"); Marek Rochowski (request for comments); Gian-Carlo Rota (mathematical encyclopedia, some correspondence form Menger on same topic); Robert Rosenthal (query from U. of Chicago libraries of Carl Menger's papers); Ludwig Reich (1978 Symposium on Functional Equations); Haim Reingold (appeal to Carnegie Corporation on Menger's behalf); John F. Randolph (comment on note by J. Novak)
  - Sagoroff, Slawtscho, 1963 (Box 4)
    German economist, Director of Vienna Institute for Advanced Studies.
    Topic(s): Invitation and acceptance to lecture at the Insitute for Advanced Studies Vienna
  - Schalie, Eric van der, 1972-1975 and undated (Box 4)
    German-English translator of Menger's "Moral, Wille und Weltgestaltung". Some outgoing correspondence.
    Topic(s): Regarding English translation of Menger's "Moral, Wille und Weltgestaltung"
  - Schein, Boris, 1965-1983 (Box 4)
    Russian-American mathematician. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Topic(s): Regarding algebra (superassociative sysmtes, multiplace functions); comments on publications; routine exchange
  - Schlick, Moritz, 1924(?), 1934-1935 (Box 4)
    German philosopher and physicist; founding member of the Vienna Circle.
    Topic(s): Routine exchange
  - Scholz, Heinrich, 1929-1939 (Box 4)
    German logician, philosopher, and theologian.
  - Schreier, Otto, 1921-1928 and undated (Box 4)
    Austrian mathematician.
    Topic(s): Routine exchange; miscellaneous mathematical discussions; comments on university classes and publications
  - Schröter, Karl, 1955-1969 (Box 4)
    Topic(s): Journal "Zeitschrift fuer Mathematische Logik und Grundlagen der Mathematik"; conference invitation
  - Schweizer, Berthold, 1953-1974 and undated (Box 4)
    Mathematician; student of Karl Menger. Some outgoing correspondence.
    Topic(s): Routine exchange; miscellaneous mathematical discussions; comments on publications; includes some photocopies of publications by others
  - Sierpiński, Waclaw, 1926-1933 (Box 4)
  - Simon and Schuster, Inc. Publishers, 1959 and undated (Box 4)
    Topic(s): Correspondance about a possible book publication
  - Skala, Helen, 1968-1972 and undated (Box 4)
    Topic(s): Routine exchange; miscellaneous mathematical discussions
  - Sklar, Abe, 1962-1981 and undated (Box 4)
    American mathematician; colleague of Karl Menger at Illinois Institute of Technology.
    Topic(s): Routine exchange; algebraic discussions
  - Springer Verlag, 1934-1981 and undated (Box 4)
    Viennese publishing house; some outgoing correspondence
    Topic(s): Correspondance about the publication and English translation of Menger's "Moral, Wille und Weltgestaltung" and about the publcation of a memorial volume for Mortiy Schlick
  - Sugar, Alvin C., 1955-1963 (Box 4)
    Topic(s): Thermodynamics, relativity
  - General correspondence, "S", 1921-1982 and undated (Box 4)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with S. Some outgoing correspondence.
  - Tarski, Alfred, 1930-1953 (Box 4)
    Polish logician, mathematician, and philosopher.
    Topic(s): Invitation to Vienna; comments on a articles by Tarski and Menger
  - Taussky-Todd, Olga, 1929-1981 and undated (Box 4)
    Austrian-American mathematician; member of Menger's Mathematical Colloquium.
    Topic(s): Abelian group; group theory; comments on manuscripts; routine exchange
  - Trillas-Ruiz, Enrique, 1967-1977 (Box 4)
    Spanish mathematician. Some outgoing correspondence.
  - General correspondence, "T", 1926-1977 and undated (Box 4)
    Other correspondents with last name beginning with T. Some outgoing correspondence.
  - Unidentified correspondents, 1921-1982 and undated; 3 folders (Box 4)